of all the things Shaw has done in his
career one of the things he's never done
has been agile so that's something that
he's going to have to learn and that's
going to be really exciting for us to
see look the news at the Olympic Games
and weightlifting is often when a woman
wins a weight category and they're not
from China right like that is a news
story honestly the equipment that they
use sitting out in the extreme heat
becomes very difficult and we've seen
that actually affect the competition in
meaningful
ways welcome to another fantastic yeah
I'm not burying the lead fantastic
edition of strength weekly the show that
keeps you updated from well all aspects
and all corners of the globe when it
comes to the barbell game and stones and
even MMA we touch on that today before
we get into that make sure to subscribe
to barbend on YouTube we would really
super appreciate it I'm David Thomas to
joined by the incomparable they were
Irreplaceable the extraordinary Phillip
Blackman and we're bringing you lots of
news from around the strength game
including what happens when a 400lb
strong man beats up on some people we
have the World's Strongest Man location
and dates for
2024 we also have a world record
cleaning
jerk Goa and then a strength tip you're
going to love so how do you get stronger
after 40 years old Phil the first story
we're going to get into today is Brian
Shaw
who is retired from Strongman
Competition went out on a very high note
by the way he's a four-time four-time
world strongest man look Brian Shaw he's
gonna enter the cage or the Octagon or
whatever he's gonna beat up on some
people at least that's what he hopes to
do he's fighting February 2024 we know
that we don't know who he's fighting
Brian Shaw MMA Phil man you're the
strong man expert take it away what what
you got for me yeah so he's going to
fight on he's going to make his MMA
debut in the open category which just
means that doesn't have to make weight
at all he's just a big guy he gets to do
big guy stuff and it's the fight's
scheduled right now to take place on
February 17th in Cutter and the prize
payout is expected to be absolutely
insane for this MMA tournament not only
will Brian Shaw be fighting at this
event but so will Eddie Hall and so will
Mitchell Hooper who's the rainning
world's strongest man champion and
notably this is going to take place two
weeks before the Arnold strongman
classic which Hooper is scheduled to
compete at as the defending Champion so
there there's a there there's a lot
going on here so it's going to be Eddie
Hall versus Mitchell Hooper now we don't
know necessarily who Brian Shaw is going
to face however we do know that Martin
FJ the actor and stunt man who's also a
gigantic human is scheduled to fight at
this event and there has been like you
know the the Rumblings that it's going
to be Ford versus Shaw although that is
not confirmed anywhere so far Brian Shaw
competing in the open
category makes more sense than anything
I've ever heard because the next weight
C cut off in in MMA you have to be under
265 right it's a lot of way it'd be a
lot of way to cut yeah I mean let let
the guy learn how to actually grapple
you know like give him time he he can't
make weight he gotta learn how to
Grapple Brian Shaw competed at at or
above 400 pounds for a lot of his
strongman career and he competed at like
a relatively lean for that sport 400
plus pounds no way that man's ever
getting down to 260 of all the things
Shaw has done in his career one of the
things he's never done has been agile so
that something that he's going to have
to learn and that's going to be really
exciting for us to see like he's he's
training with Frank Mir that's like yeah
what what we saw is that he he's
training with a multiple time UFC
heavyweight former heavyweight champion
and the biggest takeaway that he got
from that Beyond like proper grips when
you're on the ground how to escape from
underneath to move into a top position
like beyond all that the thing that he
learned the most he's like all these
things have to take in energy
conservation and that's doubly so if
you're a guy his size I want to read a
quote according to Brian Shaw I will
approach this just like I have
approached everything else put this in
front of me give me a deadline give me
an MMA match I am going to win I'm going
in to dominate look that's scary if
Brian Shaw tells me that I am fight ORF
flight response I'm either on the ground
curled up or I'm running the other way
you know I do want to say it is not
unpre what Mitchell Hooper is doing
fighting during the prime of his
strongman career is unprecedented but
what is not unprecedented is a World's
Strongest Man competitor a multi-time
world Strongest Man competitor a
four-time plus world Strongest Man
Champion moving into MMA Marius panowski
of Poland after he retired from World's
Strongest Man is still actually
competing in MMA about 14 almost 15
years later and has had an up and down
career he's fought under a number of
different banners he's had some wins had
some losses some draws he's had an up
and down career but it's not
unprecedented Brian Shaw is just a
massive human and it adds I think in my
mind an intimidation factor for anyone
who steps in the ring with him it kind
of reminds me of one of Thor bjornson's
first fights where he was gearing up we
knew the Eddie Hall fight was coming but
it kind of kept getting delayed there
were injuries there were like you know
things like that and Devon lat who is a
former Special Forces member and also
Pro armed wrestler stepped up to fight
Hof Thor and was like very clearly
outmatched in the boxing ring and even
in the postgame the postf fight
interview it was like man I'm glad Thor
didn't do more damage he was just like
honestly I'm glad Thor didn't like end
my life right now if you yeah if you go
back to that lat had like two weeks like
his short notice was the shortest of
short like it was like hey can you get
here on time and then we'll figure it
out you know he knew we all knew that
was a tune that was really a tuneup My
Hope Is that whoever whomever fights
Brian Shaw we don't know who it is yet
my My Hope Is that they're it's more
than a two- we notice right I I really
want want to see I want to I think we
all want to see a match right that's
what we want to see I I would expect
that you want some amount of competition
unless you're getting some kind of
really spectacular firstr blowout but I
I I don't expect that that's in the
cards for guys that have never fought
before because how do you make that kind
of move if you don't actually know you
know we got to move on because we need
to go back to the realm of strongman
itself Phil the 2024 World's Strongest
Man is returning to South Carolina but
things are a little bit different this
year you have covered world strongest
man competition on the ground for the
last few years I consider you the
handsomest journalist in strong man no
offense to anyone else they're all
they're all wonderful people Phil
World's Strongest Man 2024 what you got
for me returning to Myrtle bleach South
Carolina for the second year in a row
from May 1st to May 5th a competition
where there will be two days in the
qualifying stage where athletes are
paired up in groups and then the winner
and runner up of those groups advance to
the final after a stone off and then the
two-day final will take place on the
fourth and the fifth and this year that
there's going to be somewhat of a
difference and I'll give you guys a
little bit of rundown on what it's like
to actually be covering the event live
typically there are two stages or at
least last year at Myrtle Beach there
are two stages where events take place
one uh is set up while another one is
happening and it lets the crew sort of
get a head start but that always poses
some amount of problems because the
equipment that they use sitting out in
the extreme heat becomes very difficult
and we've seen that actually affect the
competition in meaningful ways so uh
examples of this is the Li ladder where
the stage had gotten so hot where the
deadlift ladder was that caka actually
had to hop off the stage and didn't
complete the deadlift ladder not because
he was incapable but because the floor
was too hot for his feet and so he had
to hop off because it hurt that's that
that's like the kind of thing you don't
want to have happen at the world stage
so I think that the adjustment from two
stages to one is taking into account how
do we minimize that kind of that kind of
result be from the elements rather than
what the athletes are actually capable
of Phil are you going to bring sunscreen
and sun protection this year because I
remember uh the first year you went to
world's strongest man you got a little
toasty just a reminder Phil I think it
is still insane that the World's
Strongest Man is held in the densest
heat in the hottest places in the world
at when it was held in Sacramento
California and I covered it every year
that it was in Sacramento and literally
the average heat in Sacramento in the
middle of the summer is 108° and they're
like let's do it away from all the trees
let's just do it in the center in the
open it's just it's chaos these guys are
already 400 lb they have breathing
problems as it is why why would you put
them in 100 degree Heat and the same at
middle Beach at least it's on the it's
literally on the beach where there's a a
bit of a breeze it's a little bit better
but yeah uh definitely bring your
sunscreen if you're gonna go watch it
live I forgot a hat the first year and I
had to get like this really weird like
brimmed hat and I it has bananas on the
brim and if you've seen me cover any of
the videos for World's Strongest Man for
barbend you'll see that I wear the
banana brim hat as a bit because I'm
known to the crew over there as banana
brim guy so it's a whole thing David
it's a whole thing look it makes for
great TV it makes for great lighting I
mean you want to see these guys sweat
you want to see them work it is a it is
made for TV and it is great
entertainment let's move on to something
that is not held in the heat in the
outside normally and that's
weightlifting the IW of Grand Prix that
wrapped up about a week ago in DOA we
talked about some of these World Records
in last uh week's broadcast
uh Olivia re of the United States Carlos
nass Bulgaria well Ling X which I might
be saying incorrectly but I am trying of
China in the women's 81 kilogram
category set a new world record at 161
kilograms she was the first to do it in
the clean jerk with 161 kilograms
beautiful looking lift and I want to
point out she is a member of the Chinese
women's weightlifting team which is the
deepest roster of
weightlifters on the planet
and by the way as an 81 kilogram athlete
this cleaning jerk was just a couple
kilos under the American record for
super
Heavies it's a lot of weight yeah that
that's what I think is the most telling
sign of like how insane and how far
ahead the the Chinese team is from
everybody else that their 81 kilo
lifters are lifting more than super
heavy weight lifters everywhere else in
the world like that that that's that's
the G right yeah I mean look the news at
the Olympic Games and weightlifting is
often when a woman wins a weight
category and they're not from China
right like that is a news story honestly
and it's also worth noting that the
grand PRI are uh qualifying events for
Paris 2024 so like we are likely to see
her compete again in the 81 kilogram
category as long as this like continues
until we get to the summer for those of
us who aren't setting World Records our
strength tip of the week is actually a
series of tips for how to get stronger
over 40 but really I think this applies
to anyone who is excited to get stronger
make improvements maybe it's on strength
body composition you name it and they're
also trying to do this with a lifestyle
that is very busy where strength
training maybe isn't their number one
priority maybe they have career family
other
obligations and you're not in your 20s
anymore right I mean my plan when I get
to 4041 is to weigh 400b b68 and get
invited to a $300 million MMA tournament
cutter that's really where I'm that's my
target that you know you got to manifest
stuff for yourself folks you got to you
got to put it out there uh I think's
been reading the secret I I I think that
the the thing to to do more I think
people naturally as they get older and
you know take on additional things in
their lives whether it's you know the
kind of job that they lead they start
families and things like that uh I think
you just lose the sense of like your
typical day-to-day activity that is
physical so uh I know that we we have an
example here which is just to walk more
I think that encapsulates uh just being
more consistently active I know we've
talked about it on previous episodes
before but consistency really is
everything and it's like we talked about
the 12 330 method on our last our
previous episode uh during the holiday
episode where you know you just get on
the treadmill for a half hour at a
reasonable intensity and you just do
that and it's like it doesn't take long
it keeps you active like body at rest
tends to stay at rest right like you
just got to get up and move even if it's
not uh super intense training and I
think consistency over the long term is
a big deal for that and then it's also
the easiest way to maneuver around a
schedule particularly if you're one
that's intense with uh deep travel
schedule deep work schedule Family Life
taking care of children etc etc all
right so I'm just going to read through
these tips here first is get your
protein protein very important
macronutrient I've talked to Dr Jim
stani about this on the podcast I
believe a couple times on the barbin
podcast as well as for articles your
protein requirements may actually
increase with age when it comes to
active lifestyle muscle maintenance and
muscle building so just keep that in
mind get your protein we've got some
great resources resources on barbend for
protein tracking only gets more
important as you age by the way because
the body gets a little less efficient at
protein synthesis so you might actually
need more protein in your diet to get
similar results that's thing number one
adjusting exercise selection Phil you
kind of touched upon this you know what
I used to really really love I used to
love snatch balances you know what
doesn't treat me so well these days
snatch balances whatever goals are
should really equate to what your
exercise selection should be so um but
something that I've adjusted to recently
I've had a lot of uh injuries on my
right leg in particular and so my
Mobility on my right ankle is uh much
worse than my left and so I'm constantly
compensating for that when I do things
like a heavy barbell Squat and so a lot
of the times when I get into that space
if I'm not sufficiently warmed up and
things like that I'll move and do more
uh accessory exercises to compensate for
the fact that like putting a heavy
barbell on my back is just not easy on
my right ankle after the
and equating is that there's a lot ofy
works because compound excises are just
that they are built from multiple uh
exercises put together essentially and
just you know you don't have to go break
away from the basics too hard to get the
workout that you're looking for training
volume modulating training and volume
intensity and intensity is important
look the most important thing as you age
might be just the realization that you
kind of you might need to train less
that doesn't mean you need to stop
training that but that means that you
might need more recovery between bouts
of exercise right and honestly I think
is what I as I've started to realize
that I've realized that for a lot of my
20s and early 30s I was actually
overtraining right and I'm recovering
better and as I prioritize recovery I
feel better recovery also more important
as I age you can get your eight to 12
sets per muscle group in any time during
the week it can be in two sessions four
sessions whatever it needs to be the the
total cumulative volume at the end of
the week is really ultimately what is
more important than any than you know
working out four to five times a week so
as long as you're you're you're training
with enough intensity which just means
that you're going to muscular Muscular
failure or if your goal is hypertrophy
that if it's easier for you to Train
full body twice a week and that's what
you recover from do it if you need to go
four times a week and break it up upper
body lower body whatever that is but you
get the same number of sets in that you
would if you had trained twice a week
great that has shown to be effective and
that's that's where the position stand
is right now on the research
another thing I want to say that's not
antithetical to that is D loads right d
loads can be really useful if used
appropriately if you are experiencing
cumulative wear and tear and you
honestly feel fried physiologically
neurologically a D Lo week where you're
not stopping to move but you are really
dialing back training intensity and
volume for a temporary period of time
while still working on some movement
patterns and staying active which does
promote recovery that can be really
useful it's something that we that
strength athletes who are used to
periodize training they know ding before
a competition deling between training
Cycles they know but it's something that
even folks who are not actively
competing can take a lesson from right
so I think that when I was a competitive
strength athly yes D loads are baked in
my coach baked those in since I'm not
really competing these days I don't
necessarily think to D Lo but those can
still be impactful periods and can help
with long-term progress uh walking more
is walking the most underrated exercise
like even for strength athletes I think
it is actually I think it is just
because it's too it sounds too easy you
want to recover better from training
walk more like honestly you're not going
to like walk off your gains but you want
to recover better walk just walk more
like it sounds stupid but it's good for
Mobility it's good for cardiovascular
health it's good for weight management
it's good for Recovery like it will
actually improve your recovery from
intense strength training walking
anecdotally for me has greatly improved
my recovery it's greatly improved my
mental health and well-being and I think
it's something that strength athletes
should focus more on and that's
something that my old school
weightlifting coaches always used to
tell me you should walk more the last
thing I want to point out Phil because I
know you agree with that because you're
the one who introduced it variety
mobility and core work become more
important as you
age body weight training Pilates Yoga
Core specific training something that's
been important for me as I get as I get
older but I still want to maintain
activity levels the migil big three
right which you can look up on barbend
we can link it in the description below
maybe a card here these are all things
that have been shown to improve
recovery allowing your body a greater
opportunity an improved opportunity to
heal and recover between intensive
intensive bouts of strength training and
that is the key here as you age recovery
more and more important Phil I'm going
to hop off the Soap Box do you want to
hop on for even just a second to wrap
that up yeah I'm just going to continue
a theme Here on strength weekly oh you
think you're strong you think you're a
powerful strong human go take a pilates
class take a pilates class you ain't
strong you ain't strong you ain't strong
take a pilates class you ain't Pilates
strong not no you ain't Pilates strong
if you ain't taking pilates
class it is humbling Humble Pie well we
love eating Humble Pie here on strength
weekly it's our favorite holiday dish
and that will bring you the end of
strength weekly the last episode of the
year but we'll be back we'll be back in
early January we're not going far for
too long happy holidays folks for
strength weekly I'm David Thomas toow
joined by Phil bman I got to go and uh
you know live up to what I just said I'm
going to go do some
Pilates practice what we preach happy
holidays folks catch you in the new
[Music]
year